Guide to the Bristow Adams papers, 1853-1970, 1862-1957 (bulk)
Adams, Bristow papers, 1853-1970
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Bristow Adams papers, 1853-1970, 1862-1957 (bulk)
3205
Bristow Adams, 1875-1957.
15.1 cubic ft; 18 drawings.
Correspondence, published and unpublished articles, press releases, illustrations, newspapers, pamphlets, clippings, posters, periodicals, drawings, paintings, lecture notes, essays, college memorabilia, photographs, creative writings, and other materials.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Consists of papers of Bristow Adams, journalist, professor, forester, and illustrator. Various materials document his journalistic career, including early work with a paper in D.C.; his editorial responsibilities on Stanford University publications; and his work as publications program director for the College of Agriculture at Cornell. From his student years are sketches of fur seals; college memorabilia; and many letters to his mother. Also, photographs from work for the US Forest Service; photographs of the Cornell track team; Cornell student publications; and creative writings. Also, various materials chronicling his life, including his acting mayor of Ithaca. This collection also contains papers of Adams' father, primarily concerning his Civil War service.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Benjamin Bristow Adams was born to Crawford Cadwallader and Ada G. Harrison Adams in Washington, D.C., November 11, 1875. He, three younger sisters and one younger brother were left fatherless in 1885. From the age of ten he was forced to help support his family and was frequently boarded out to relatives on a Virginia farm with his younger brother. He attended Central High School in Washington from 1890-1892 and advanced in the school cadet corps. In 1892 he left school to become co-founder and editor of a weekly magazine, the "Pathfinder." The magazine began as a weekly news review for children but evolved into a paper for the benefit of "current events" teachers.
In 1896 Bristow left for the west to start college at the newly established university of Stanford. He paid his trip west with money earned during summers as a lifeguard at the Washington Public Bathing Beach, Big Basin. He intended to work for his room and board at college; tuition was free. He entered Stanford by exam, not application. Consequently he attended under the status of a special student. He concentrated in drawing and painting his first two years, and English in his last two. He was to have graduated in 1900 as an English major with a concentration in drawing, but because he was short one credit he was not given a diploma. In 1906 David Starr Jordan, professor and president of Stanford, awarded Bristow his belated diploma despite the lack of one credit.
During his college years Bristow pursued his interests in art and journalism. At the end of his freshman year, David Starr Jorden, chairman of the Bering Sea Fur Seal Commission, appointed Bristow artist for the commission. For five months, Bristow made observations and sketches of the fur seals of the Pribilof Islands. These sketches were later used to illustrate the commission's three volume report. Bristow had pursued his art training some years before at the Spring Garden Institute in Philadelphia and the Corcoran Art School in Washington, D.C. While at Stanford, he studied at the Barron Studios.
Following his journalistic bent to pay his room and board, Bristow did writing by correspondence for the Seattle Post Intelligencer and the Boston Transcript. Bristow also edited all of the Stanford publications, without monetary recompense, during his four years at that institution. He also founded and edited the "Stanford Chaparral," 1898-1900, the first college humor magazine in the west.
After completing four years of studies at Stanford Bristow returned to work on the "Pathfinder" in Washington, D.C. He continued to work as a free-lance writer and illustrator for magazines including "McClure's," "Everybody's," "Country Life in America," and the "Washington Star."
In 1902 he married Luella Farmer whom he had met in a freshman art class at Stanford. They had conducted their courtship through extensive correspondence since 1900. Soon after marrying they had four children: Eleanor, Gertrude, Everett and Benjamin Bristow II. The growth and development of the family is documented in the correspondence.
In 1904 Bristow became vice president of H. M. Suter Publishing Company where he designed a series of college athletic posters, edited "Forestry and Irrigation," forerunner "American Forests" and was managing editor of a weekly news review, "Washington Life" later called "American Spectator."
Bristow was asked to join the U.S. Forest Service in 1906, in their office of Information. There he edited bulletins and issued news reports. From the information he absorbed editing and writing articles on forestry, he was able to pass the civil service technical forestry examination. Subsequently he became a forestry assistant in the Choctawatchee National Forest in west Florida. There he was involved in introducing exotic tree species: eucalyptus, Australian wattle, cork oak and French maritime pine. As a result of his work and research in this area Stanford elected him to Sigma Xi, an honorary scientific organization.
While in the forestry service, Bristow became a member of the Society of American Foresters, and was elected to the post of secretary and representative. In this capacity he attended the dedication of Fernow Hall at Cornell in May 1914. He spent the summer of 1914 visiting many of the state and national forests in the Rockies and far west as a forest examiner.
November 1914, Bristow accepted a position at Cornell University as a full professor in the Agricultural School and department head in charge of publications and information.. As a professor he started courses in journalism, advertising and publicity, and forestry and conservation. Bristow, familiarly known as B.A. by generations of Cornellians, became an immediate favorite with the students. He encouraged their friendship through his weekly Monday night open house or "at homes" at 202 Fall Creek Drive. There students congregated in the second floor study listening to anecdotes of Bristow's travel, discussing current events, airing their problems and enjoying Mrs. Adams' delicious home-made hot chocolate and cookies.
Aside from professorial tasks, Bristow started the mimeograph news service and supervised the Extension Publications and the Experiment Station Bulletins. During the thirty years he taught and edited at Cornell, the University won more awards for excellence of the printed word than any other Land Grant College.
Combining his love of students with his love of journalism, Bristow became a member of the board of directors of the "Cornell Daily Sun" and unofficial advisor to the "Cornell Countryman" and the "Cornell Widow." Bristow pursued many other jobs and activities relating to his journalistic interests while a forester and professor. In 1909 he was a public director of the National Milk Show and Dairy Exposition in New York City; in 1923 he served in the same capacity for the World's Dairy Congress. During World War I in 1918, Bristow took a temporary leave from the University and joined the U.S. Department of Agriculture's campaign for stimulation of food production. From that work he progressed to the Military Intelligence Division of the General Staff of the Army, where he was engaged in counter-espionage and counter-propaganda, as liaison officer with the Commission on Public Information, The Department of Justice, and the Military Morale Branch. In 1921 he wrote Fanner's bulletin 1202, "An Agricultural Almanac" for the U.S. Department of Agriculture For six months in 1930, he taught a conservation and natural resources course at the University of Hawaii. In the early thirties he was made regional director for the Federal Writer's Project (WPA) in New York. He retained this position until he was dismissed by Henry G. Alsberg, for unsuccessful completion of work. Actually he was dismissed for charging Wallace Miller, who posed as a Stanford graduate, with being a communist and recommending his removal from the project. This affair got wide publicity and brought Bristow into the national headlines. Finally, in 1939, Bristow was given an reward for appreciation of service by the New York Press Association.
Bristow pursued interests aside from journalism in his spare time. He had gone out for track while in college and retained an active interest in the sport while at Cornell. He was a referee for over 30 years, officiating evening games in full evening dress tails, white tie, white gloves, and top hat. In 1924 he visited England with the Cornell and Princeton track teams as they competed against Oxford and Cambridge. In 1926 Bristow visited continental Europe, studying farming and agricultural techniques.
Bristow's artistic and literary talents allowed him to earn enough money to pay for two trips around the world. In 1930 he traveled around the world north of the equator, in 1937-1938 he traveled around the world south of the equator. From the great variety of experiences of his travels, Bristow gave years of monthly talks over WGY in Schenectady, entitled "The World and Us." He also broadcast a weekly book review, "Let's Read a Book" over the Cornell Radio Station for over fifteen years.
Bristow retired in 1943 but was immediately reappointed by the Trustees for an additional year of service. He was made Professor Emeritus in 1944 and once again recalled to serve through 1945. In July 1945 he was asked to teach courses in the summer session. In 1938, 1939, and 1941 he also taught a summer session in Extension Methods conducted by Colorado State College at Fort Collins. There he taught editing, extension writings and publicity methods in extension.
Bristow had planned for years to spend his retirement doing oil painting and gardening. Although he did manage to do one art show, he was never able to pursue this interest as much as he liked. He became alderman for the Ithaca Town Council, then acting mayor of Ithaca for seven years, retiring the year before his death. He also founded and edited the "Cornell Plantations," a quarterly publication from 1942-1956. These activities plus his obligations in radio broadcasting, and numerous duties and organizations to which he belonged amply filled his time. Among the various honorary organizations and clubs which he belonged to during his life were: National Press Club; Society of American Foresters (Secretary, 1913); New York Press Association (life membership and Director-at-large); Sigma Delta Chi, professional journalism society (National Honorary President, 1920); American Association of Agricultural College Editors, (president, 1921); American Association of Teachers of Journalism; Sigma Xi; Alpha Gamma Rho; Epsilon Sigma Phi; Savage Club of Ithaca.
B.A. died, after a year of illness in a nursing home, in November 1956. He was survived by his wife, Luella, four children and four grandchildren.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Consists primarily of papers of Bristow Adams (1875-1957), journalist, professor, forester, and illustrator. Correspondence, published and unpublished articles, press releases, illustrations, newspapers, pamphlets, clippings, posters, and periodicals document his journalistic career beginning with his early work on The Pathfinder (1894-1895), a current affairs weekly published in Washington, D.C., of which he was a co-founder and associate editor, and including editorial responsibilities on Stanford University student publications, The Daily Palo Alto, The Stanford Sequoia, and a college humor magazine, The Stanford Chapparal, of which he was a founder; work on Washington, D.C. journals, Washington Life, American Spectator, and Forestry and Irrigation; his work as publications program director for the New York State College of Agriculture at Cornell University (1914-1945); and his editorship of Cornell Plantations (1944-1957). Also documenting his student years are sketches of fur seals and other drawings done in the Pribilof Islands while he was an artist for the Bering Sea Fur Seal Commission (1897); lecture notes, essays, and college memorabilia; and many letters to his mother, Ada G. Harrison Adams. Numerous photographs document his work for the United States Forest Service (1906-1914).
Other activities while Adams was at Cornell are evidenced by teaching materials from his courses in journalism and conservation of natural resources; photographs of the Cornell track team, for which he was faculty advisor for twenty-five years; student publications, The Delicate Brown and The Cornell Widow, for which he was faculty advisor; scripts for radio programs regularly broadcast on WGY, Schenectady, NY, or WHCU, Ithaca, NY; and many speeches and creative writings, poetry, jokes, plays and short stories. Also include many drawings, paintings, and scrapbooks of clippings (1908-1956) chronicling his life, including his brief tenure as director of the WPA writers' project in New York and his participation in municipal politics as an alderman and, on occasion, acting mayor of Ithaca, NY (1946-1954). His numerous correspondents include Henry G. Alsberg, Margaret Bourke-White, Sherwin Cody, Charles Collingwood, Edmund Ezra Day, A.W. Gibson, David B. Greenberg, Lester W. Herzog, David Starr Jordan, Russell Lord, Deane W. Malott, Albert R. Mann, Gifford Pinchot, Anastasia J. Romanoff, Theodore Roosevelt, Elihu Root, Harold M. Schmeck, Jr., Jacob Gould Schurman, William Howard Taft, Robert E. Treman, Peter Vischer, E.B. White, and Lee A. White. His family life is reflected by extensive correspondence with his wife, Luella Farmer Adams, and many other family members (1880-1957) and family photoprints.
This collection also contains papers of Adams' father, Crawford Cadwallader Adams (1839-85), primarily concerning his Civil War service in the 14th Ohio Infantry, but also including his certificate of appointment as a Special Agent of the Treasury Department (1877) and a journal containing excerpts from his correspondence with his future wife, Ada G. Harrison; and papers of Elmer E. Farmer Creighton (1878-1928), electrical engineer, primarily letters from his mother, Eleanor Creighton Farmer, brothers, Fred B. Farmer and Clyde C. Farmer, sister, Luella Farmer Adams, friends, and professional colleagues written to him while he was studying and teaching at Stanford University (1891-1897, 1901), participating in the Bering Sea Fur Seal Commission expedition to the Pribilof Islands (1897), studying at the Sorbonne in Paris (1898-1900), and working for the Stanley Electric Manufacturing Company, Pittsfield, MA (1901-1904) and for the General Electric Company and Union College, Schenectady, NY (1904-1927), after the Stanley Company became part of General Electric; also includes letters from others to his mother, who lived with him during the 1920's, technical notes, clippings, information concerning a gold mine he operated, and college memorabilia.
Includes correspondence of Bristow Adams while he was a member of the Bering Sea Fur Seal Commission.
Also, eighteen Ivy League athletic posters drawn by Adams.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Adams, Bristow, 1875-1957.; Adams, Crawford Cadwallader.; Adams, Luella Farmer.; Alsberg, Henry G. (Henry Garfield), 1881-1970.; Bourke-White, Margaret, 1904-1971.; Cody, Sherwin, 1868-1959.; Collingwood, Charles.; Creighton, Elmer E. Farmer.; Day, Edmund Ezra, 1883-1951.; Farmer, Clyde C.; Farmer, Eleanor Creighton.; Farmer, Fred B.; Gibson, A. W.; Greenberg, David B. (David Benjamin), 1892-1968.; Harrison, Ada G.; Herzog, Lester W.; Jordan, David Starr, 1851-1931.; Lord, Russell, 1895-1964.; Malott, Deane W. (Deane Waldo), 1898-; Mann, Albert Russell, 1880-1947.; Pinchot, Gifford, 1865-1946.; Romanoff, Anastasia J., 1905-; Roosevelt, Theodore, 1858-1919.; Root, Elihu, 1845-1937.; Schmeck, Harold M.; Schurman, Jacob Gould, 1854-1942.; Taft, William H. (William Howard). 1857-1930.; Treman, Robert E. (Robert Elias), 1888-1953.; Vischer, Peter.; White, E. B. (Elwyn Brooks), 1899-; White, Lee A., b.1886.; Bering Sea Fur Seal Commission.; Cornell University.; Federal Writers' Project (N.Y.); General Electric Company (Schenectady, N.Y.); Ivy League (Athletic conference).; New York State College of Agriculture.; Stanley Electric Manufacturing Company (Pittsfield, Mass.); Union College (Schenectady, N.Y.); United States. Forest Service.
Titles:
Pathfinder.; Forestry and irrigation.; Cornell plantations.
Subjects:
Electric engineers.; Forests and forestry.; Athletics; Journalists.; Foresters.; Artists.
Places:
United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.; New York (State)--Politics and government.
Form and Genre Terms:
Paintings.; Scrapbooks.; Photographs.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
SERIES LIST
Series I. Elmer E. F. Creighton Papers, 1886-1928
Subseries A. Correspondence
Boxes 1-7
Subseries B. Business and Financial Papers
Box 7
Subseries C. Creative Writings
Box 7
Subseries D. Technical Notes
Box 8
Subseries E. Memorabilia
Box 8
Series II. Bristow Adams Papers
Subseries A. Correspondence
Boxes 9-31
Subseries B. Radio Talks
Boxes 32-33
Subseries C. Articles (published and unpublished)
Boxes 34-35
Subseries D. Speeches
Box 35
Subseries E. Creative Writing
Boxes 35-37
Subseries F. Biographical Writing
Box 37
Subseries G. College Material
Boxes 37-39
Subseries H. Financial Records
Box 40
Subseries I. Publications
Boxes 40-46, 58
Subseries J. Art Work
Boxes 47-49
Subseries K. Photographs
Boxes 50-53
Subseries L. Clippings and Scrapbooks
Boxes 54-60
Subseries M. Miscellany
Box 61
Series III. Crawford Cadwallader Adams Papers
Subseries A. Correspondence and Military Papers
Boxes 62-64, 49
Series IV. Miscellaneous
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Elmer E. F. Creighton. Papers, 1886-1928
  Correspondence includes letters from his mother, Eleanor Creighton Farmer, brothers, Fred B. Farmer and Clyde C. Farmer, sister, Luella Farmer Adams, friends, and professional colleagues written to him while he was studying and teaching at Stanford University (1891-1897, 1901), participating in the Bering Sea Fur Commission expedition to the Pribilof Islands (1897), studying at the Sorbonne in Paris (1898-1900), and working for the Stanley Electric Manufacturing Company, Pittsfield, Mass. (1901-1904) and for the General Electric Company and Union College, Schenectady, N.Y. (1904-1927), after the Stanley Company became part of General Electric; and letters from others to his mother, who lived with him during the 1920's. Other series contain technical notes, clippings, information concerning a gold mine he operated, and college memorabilia.
  - Subseries A. Correspondence
    - May 5, 1886 - Dec. 26, 1891 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Jan. 24, 1892 - Dec. 28, 1892 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Jan. 11, 1893 - Apr. 30, 1893 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - May 4, 1893 - Oct. 19, 1893 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Nov. 3, 1893 - Dec. 26, 1893 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Jan. 25, 1894 - Dec. 22, 1894 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Jan. 11, 1895 - June 19, 1895 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - July 1, 1895 - Dec. 27, 1895 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Jan. 15, 1896 - July 22, 1896 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Aug. 6, 1896 - Dec. 10, 1896 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Jan. 1, 1897 - May 28, 1897 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - June 8, 1897 - Aug. 25, 1897 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Sept. 1, 1897 - Dec. 29, 1897 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Jan. 5, 1898 - Apr. 28, 1898 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - May 6, 1898 - Aug. 17, 1898 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Sept. 4, 1898 - Dec. 20, 1898 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Jan. 1, 1899 - May 17, 1899 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - June 6, 1899 - Aug. 30, 1899 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Sept. 3, 1899 - Dec. 28, 1899 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Jan. 1, 1900 - Aug. 31, 1900 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Sept. 22, 1900 - Dec. 22, 1900 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Jan. 8, 1901 - Mar. 28, 1901 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Apr. 9, 1901 - June 12, 1901 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - July 4, 1901 - Sept. 16, 1901 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Oct. 6, 1901 - Dec. 28, 1901 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Jan. 2, 1902 - Apr. 26, 1902 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - May 9, 1902 - June 23, 1902 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - July 3, 1902 - Dec. 19, 1902 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Jan. 27, 1903 - Dec. 23, 1903 (Box 3, Folder 9)
      Note: On June 3, 1903 the Probate Court of Berkshire Cty., MA. changed the name of Elmer F. Farmer to Elmer E. F. Creighton in accordance with the wishes of his late maternal grandfather, David Creighton.
    - Jan. 11, 1904 - Dec. 21, 1904 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Jan. 1905 - Dec. 31, 1905 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Jan. 1, 1906 - Nov. 9, 1906 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Jan. 3, 1907 - Nov. 15, 1909 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Jan. 2, 1910 - Dec. 17, 1911 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Jan. 3, 1912 - Dec. 25, 1912 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Jan. 8, 1913 - Sept. 29, 1913 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Oct. 5, 1913 - Dec. 26, 1913 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Jan. 4, 1914 - May 28, 1914 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - June 4, 1914 - Dec. 26, 1914 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Jan. 3, 1915 - Dec. 27, 1915 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Jan. 10, 1916 - June 19, 1916 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - July 18, 1916 - Dec. 27, 1916 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Jan. 1, 1917 - Dec. 6, 1917 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Jan. 11, 1918 - Dec. 16, 1918 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Jan. 7, 1919 - Aug. 28, 1919 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Sept. 4, 1919 - Oct. 31, 1919 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Nov. 4, 1919 - Dec. 31, 1919 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Jan. 5, 1920 - Feb. 26, 1920 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Mar. 6, 1920 - June 19, 1920 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - July 8, 1920 - Dec. 22, 1920 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Jan. 15, 1921 - May 3, 1921 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - June 16, 1921 - Dec. 27, 1921 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Jan. 8, 1922 - Dec. 25, 1922 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Feb. 20, 1923 - Sept. 30, 1923 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Oct. 3, 1923 - Dec. 25, 1923 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Jan. 2, 1924 - Apr. 26, 1924 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - June 1, 1924 - Dec. 26, 1924 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Jan. 7, 1925 - Nov. 3, 1925 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Feb. 6, 1926 - Dec. 30, 1926 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Jan. 2, 1927 - May 5, 1927 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - June 6, 1927 - Oct. 26, 1927 (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Nov. 1, 1927 - Oct. 28, 1928 (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - n.d. (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - n.d. (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - n.d. (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - n.d. (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - n.d. (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - n.d. (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - n.d. (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Subseries B. Business and Financial Papers
    - Horsehead Mine Papers. 1922-1923 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Receipts (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Subseries C. Creative Writings
    - Poems, essays (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Poems, prose (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - Poems, prose (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Subseries D. Technical Notes
    - Seal Trip notes. Aug. 7 - Sept. 9, 1897 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Technical notes (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Technical notes (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Subseries E. Memorabilia
    - Photographs. 1902. Mining property and relatives (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Misc. and Stanford memorabilia (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Misc. and Stanford memorabilia (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Misc. and Stanford memorabilia (Box 8, Folder 7)
- Series II. Bristow Adams
  - Subseries A. Correspondence, 1880-1970
    Primarily personal in nature, this correspondence consists largely during the early years, of letters exchanged between Bristow and his wife, Luella Farmer Adams during their courtship and marriage, and other correspondence with family members and friends. The volume of correspondence increases after 1896 when Bristow left Washington, D. C. to attend Stanford University.
    Among the major correspondents are: